Guide to the Deer Lodge (Mont.) City Government Study Commission records 1974-1977
Montana Historical Society
Deer Lodge (Mont.) City Government Study Commission records
1974-1977
Montana Historical Society Research Center Archives
LG 14
Deer Lodge (Mont.). City Government Study Commission.
.4 linear feet of shelf space
This collection (1974-1977) consists of general correspondence, including letters exchanged between the State Local Government Study Commission, and workshop leaders, and consultants; minutes of the Deer Lodge City Government Study Commission; subject files; clippings; and miscellany.
The 1972 Montana Constitution required the legislature to "... provide procedures requiring each local government unit or combination of units to review its structure and submit one alternative form of government to the qualified electors ..." by 1976. Local governments were assisted in their endeavors by the Montana State Commission on Local Government.
The Deer Lodge City Government Study Commission was one of 182 city, town, and county local government study commissions, each of which consisted of at least three unpaid members elected in nonpartisan elections held in November 1974. The Commission conducted a review of the Deer Lodge government and recommended the "strong mayor and weak council" form of government as an alternative form of government, as well as consolidation of the city police department with the county sheriff's office. Both recommendations were rejected by the voters in a November 1976 election.
This collection consists of five series: general correspondence, which contains letters exchanged with the state commission, workshop leaders, consultants such as the Institute of the Rockies and the University of Montana, other government study commissions, etc.; minutes (1974-1977) of the Deer Lodge City Government Study Commission and the joint meetings of the Deer Lodge City and Powell County Government Study Commissions; subject files; clippings; and miscellany.
The collection is arranged by series.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
Photographs transferred to the Photo Archives.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Local government --Montana--Deer Lodge.
Deer Lodge (Mont.)--Politics and government.; Powell County (Mont.)--Politics and government.
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
- General Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous (correspondents include other local government study commissions and Deer Lodge citizens), 1974-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 1-2)
  - Institute of the Rockies, 1975 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Montana State Commission on Local Government, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
- Minutes
  - Deer Lodge City Government Study Commission, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 5-6)
  - Deer Lodge and Powell County Government Study Commissions joint meetings, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
- Photographs
  - List of photographs transferred to the Photo Archives (Box-folder 1 / 8)
- Subject Files
  - Law enforcement and proposed law enforcement service transfer from Deer Lodge to Powell County, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Proposed reapportionment plan for Deer Lodge (contains OVERSIZE MATERIAL, see oversize box), 1976 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Proposed reapportionment plan for Powell County (contains OVERSIZE MATERIAL, see map case), 1976 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Public hearing and forum, 1975 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - Survey concerning consolidation of Deer Lodge city and Powell County services, 1976 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - Survey of perceptions of Deer Lodge government, 1975 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - Survey on preferred form of government, 1976 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Workshops, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
- Clippings
  - Miscellaneous (re changing name of Deer Lodge County, airport, suggested changes in local government), 1975-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
- Miscellany
  - Proposed booklet on city government; questionnaires for students; list of city employees; newsletter; etc., 1974-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 18)
  - Questionnaire re boards, commissions, committees, councils, and special districts, 1975 (Box-folder 1 / 19)
  - Questionnaire re information about city government from city employees; responses, 1975 (Box-folder 1 / 20-21)